Hello everyone, I am Hesh Singla and
welcome to my channel. Uh so this week
we are going to talk talk about
interesting topic on the health
insurance and uh the topic that I've
chosen for this week is common health
insurance myths that you should stop
believing in as a person. Um there are
lot of uh health insurance uh uh related
myths that I get a lot of people to when
I interact with a lot of people and get
that I got to know. So uh in this video
I'll be covering all I'll try to cover
major of these myths and present them to
you uh so that any informed person can
make a better decision on uh how to go
about buying your health insurance plan.
So let's start discussing the major
myths. The first is the uh with
sufficient saving health insurance
redundant.
This is for this statement is
immediately given by people who are not
aware that these days the cost of
hospitalization can run into lack lacks
of rupees and this could actually uh
cause a financial crunch to a lot of
people. So even if you are having a lot
of saving uh done in your bank account,
the major cause of buying a health
insurance cost was too that these uh
these savings that you have done or the
any assets that you have created over
the long period of your working life are
not touched and your health are also
covered where these uh cost of lack of
rupees are covered by the health
insurance price and not by your funded
by by your savings or any other asset.
Health insurance is only for older
people or I am I do not need a health a
health cover. Uh well this um the any
kind of a disease does not look at uh
age of any of of a person. So this is
this uh this is a myth that only a older
person requires a health insurance.
Definitely the chances of getting a
disease at a at a old age is higher as
compared to a young person. But we are
in a situ in a in a world where a lot of
diseases are being contracted by the
young young people and uh the billings
the high bills of uh high bills of the
hospitals as we discussed in the first
point could be a financial burden to any
of either older or a younger person.
Another point to note is uh as as a
person get older there is a possibility
of getting a higher chance of getting uh
uh many diseases and at that point
either you will have to bear the higher
premium uh paid or uh the insurance
company can altogether decline uh
decline a uh insurance
policy. Uh you get coverage as soon as
you buy the plan. uh see as soon as you
buy the plan uh there are three waiting
periods that are applicable to any uh
policy that you buy in the market. The
first is the 30-day cooling period for
first day 30-day cooling period only
accidental uh uh claims are acceptable.
Uh and after 30 days the most of the
claims are acceptable. Uh then comes the
pre-existing diseases. pre-existing
diseases are those um which a person had
declared to the uh insurance pro service
provider that these are the pre-existing
diseases that I am I have already
contracted with and the insurance
service provider may apply a waiting
period on on those diseases. The third
part is the specified diseases. A
specified disease is a are diseases uh
listed diseases on any policies which uh
are uh which help you uh which tells the
uh person that these there are waiting
period applicable on those particular
diseases which can range from 2 to 3
years. So whenever a person is buying a
health insurance plan, it it comes
mandatory that he looks at the policy
and uh look at what all diseases could
be under the specified illness uh
waiting period. I we have already done
it for you. You can uh approach us and
we'll be happy to share that list with
you. A lot of employers these days are
providing health insurance cover to
their employees. But there are a few
things that you should keep in mind
while um saying that your employer
provided health insurance coverage is
enough for you. The first thing is that
the the limit the coverage limit is very
limited. Uh there's very less
flexibility in these plans and they may
not include riders which might be
applicable to you.
Also uh there's a condition that when we
uh it al se ceases uh this this cover
would cease when you leave the
organization. So uh take for an example
you are in between two organization and
there's a gap of 15 days. So for that 15
days you are not covered under these any
of the health insurance plan. Uh another
thing to notice at the time of
retirement since uh you were only
dependent on your employer provided
health insurance and at that age you
there might be some conditions which
might uh cause uh the if you uh apply
for a health insurance cover at that age
there that the uh health insurance
company might not be able to provide you
with the health insurance cover. Uh
cheapest plan is the best option.
Well uh this is the biggest med myth
that is uh prevailed in the market.
Price is not equivalent to the uh price
does not decide the best option.
Definitely an optimization of price
should be looked at but uh there might
be something that uh a cheap plan might
not cover the even the basic features
required. There might be some some
limits that they might have introduced.
Uh they might not be covering some
diseases. there might be some uh capping
on the room rents on the diseases that
they are covering. So there could be
various things. So uh to understand that
you you have to definitely read through
the policy wordings uh that are provided
with the uh uh with the health insurance
and a lot of people do not have time for
do not get into that. They just look at
the price and purchase the uh plan
thinking that uh uh that let's say a
person was planning uh was planning to
purchase a plan of 15 lakh he'll just
look around and go with the 15 lakh plan
from a uh of a insurer who has provided
with the least good. Now even his
thought process was to uh he got a 15
he's happy that he has a coverage of 15
lakh rupees as of now but there could be
lot of things that could be missing into
those policy in that policy because of
the cheapness of the plan. So please
definitely look into the wordings if you
are looking at a cheap buying a cheap
plan insurance cover companies cover all
expenses in in the event of
hospitalization.
Uh this is another myth cause a lot of
policies uh in their wordings have a lot
of uh star marked uh uh uh starmark
quotations which you which a lot of
people might not be reading into. So uh
these could be they could have put in
some excursion into their policy. They
might have put in co-ayments into their
policies. They could have also put in
waiting period as discussed earlier of
the pre-existing diseases. Um moreover
there could be some limits that they
might have introduced into the policy
sub limits as in case of some diseases
that they would say that even if your
policy you have taken for 15 lakh
coverage but they will pay only for this
particular disease they will only pay
two lakh rupees. So even if your
hospital bills you for five lakh rupees
of you would be only provided with two
lakh coverage from the policy.
uh they can con uh cap they can put a
cap on the room rent as a percentage of
the sum issued. Uh also uh there are uh
expenditures
uh limited to the uh non-medical
expenditures in uh whenever a
hospitalization occurs. So there are a
lot many clauses that has a person has
to look into. So just saying that uh you
have taken an insurance policy and
thinking that it will cover all the
expenses is uh is is not a wise thing to
do. You should definitely review your
policy uh policy wordings and then come
out uh look into what all things they
provided and what all things they have
excluded. Uh u we again have done this
study for you. You can reach out to us.
we can definitely would like to help you
uh in buying the best health insurance
plan. Health insurance only cover
hospitalization cost or hospitalization
is a must. Uh so this was a uh this was
a myth uh and this is a a very important
discussion point also these days there
are with the advancement of the
hospitalization the the policies are
covering daycare treatments lot of
treatments are only done on daycare
basis. Now there are policies also
available in the market which also
covers the diagnostic test. Uh policies
are covering IUS treatments. Um pre and
post medical hospitalization that is u
before you get into a hospitalization.
uh if there are text test and diagnostic
which which has led to that
hospitalization and uh post that uh
there are some treatments and visit
doctor treatments that are going on
those would be covered under the same uh
same um uh policy. So uh there are
notable procedures like chemotherapy,
radiotherapy, lithotroscopy,
uh diialysis and eye surgery which are
covered under daycare procedure and
which a lot of policies are covering
this. People who smoke and drink are not
eligible for health insurance. Uh this
is another myth I would like to break.
uh there people with lot of people who
are smoke who are habitual smoker or
habitual uh alcohol consumer are
eligible there might be some conditions
uh which might be laid by your policy uh
service provider. So they might uh help
they might
uh put some uh higher premier cost
premium cost associated with this and
they might ask for a health checkup if
they want to um want to be sure that the
uh the health of the person is at that
moment okay to cover the
risk. Failing to renew your health
insurance on time will mean loss of all
benefits.
uh all all the majorly all the policies
provide a grace period on the expiration
of your um on on the uh the expiration
of the policy period there the 50 to 30
days grace period provided and uh u
those grace period uh grace periods can
be utilized if you have missed your
payment on the last day then you need
not worry there's a time gap of 15 to 20
days pass
uh all health insurance policies are
same. So, uh this is not true. Every
company has their own health coverage
plan which they are offering. Uh you
have to look for an appleto apple
comparison and uh uh you have to look at
what the terms and conditions they are
offering in your plan and uh and you
need to choose which which uh is best
suited for you. Uh so we uh we have I
have already done this comparison. I
have created a apple-to-apple comparison
which I use it to
help my clients to buy their health
insurance plans. U the other myth is
pre-existing conditions are never
covered. Well uh this was the point that
we had discussed uh earlier that
pre-existing diseases have a waiting
period. Usually a waiting period of 1 up
to four years can are applicable. But
these days now the policies are
uh are uh are coming up with the plans
where where they charge you with the
extra premium for for a pre-existing
condition and they start this cover at a
u at the very earliest of 30 days to 90
days minimum period of time. Uh so uh
it's it it is important to also note
that uh any pre-existing condition you
should declare while buying your policy.
You should not never hide any
pre-existing uh condition. Uh network
hospital can only be found in big
cities. Well, uh this is another myth.
Uh the policies I have now flown to tier
2, tier three cities and uh every
everywhere you can find the hospitals
which will provide you the cashless
treatment. Hiding pre-existing illness
can help me get insurance. uh as already
discussed with by me uh you should
always declare any pre-existing
illnesses any major surgeries that you
have gone through while purchasing up
your policy so that uh your coverages
are not denied or even if you are you
you don't have to go into any kind of a
litigation. Uh failing a health filing a
health insurance cover claim is a
hassle. Well, um even though health
health filing claim filing is a bit of a
hassle, I would definitely agree to that
point. But now cash treatments are
available. So uh which are uh which are
very easy to do uh in the
hospitalization and uh which also
eliminates the need for any upfront
payments or claim filing for those
expenses. So um cashless treatment is a
uh is a is a truth truth of today and
you should use that facility as such uh
for filing uh whenever you are taking
your uh health insurance maternity
coverage is automatically included. A
lot of policies have stopped including
maternity cover and there were policy
earlier the policies were to only cover
the hospitalization expenses and so
maternity was not part of it. So uh so
you have to look into that your policy
that you're purchasing might not provide
you with the maternity
cover. Uh once you have insurance you
are all set. Uh this is not true as uh
insurance uh health insurance is
generally purchased for a period of 1
year and um over the years there there
are there might be some changes in your
health uh uh which might cause you to
look into for a higher sum issue. There
might be some additional riders that you
might be uh thinking to purchase. your
uh children who were uh were part of the
policy might have matured and now they
would have would would want to be
running a accepted policy. So all these
things keeps on changing. So once you
have purchased a policy it might keep uh
you might have to uh uh you might have
to keep on reviewing it at a periodical
time. Uh policy documents can be
discarded after the expiry of the
policy. Well, this is another uh myth.
uh the polic your you should not discard
any of your health insurance policy
document. Uh first thing is that they
can help your past policies can help you
help the third party administration to
help you with the claim approval
process. Um you might this might be uh
help this might help to establish a
continuous cover and uh could be uh very
crucial for smooth claim settlement.
Health insurance is too expensive. Uh a
point to note that is health insurance
plans the premiums are uh uh uh are uh
can be used for a tax deduction under
section 80D of income tax uh of income
tax health and uh this this could help
to reduce the burden on on your uh on a
financial
plan. So that was all from my side. I
hope you enjoyed this video. Uh do
share, subscribe to my channel and do uh
comment with uh any of your doubts uh or
anything that you have. Thank you.